<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-27T20:16:10+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Grounded Architecture: The Chief Architect’s Playbook</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Favorite Quotes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Favorite Quotes" /><published>2021-10-25T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-25T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/quotes"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/books-g1b2675255_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/prettysleepy-2973588/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=5430104">Amy</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=5430104">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong> Get a selection of my favorite quotes about architecture.</p>
</blockquote>

<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 12px;
     margin-top: 20px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 120%;
     font-style: italic;
 }
 .author {
     margin-top: 8px;
     font-size: 80%;
 }
</style>

<h2 id="people-people-people">People, People, People</h2>

<div class="quote">
Architecture is <b>not so much about the software</b>, <b>but about the people</b> who write the software. The core principles of architecture, such as <b>coupling and cohesion</b>, aren't about the code. The code doesn't 'care' about how cohesive or decoupled it is; … But people do care about their coupling to other team members. <div class="author">-James O. Coplien</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
Software design is <b>an exercise in human relationships</b>.
<div class="author">-Kent Beck</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
Bad software architecture is a people problem. When <b>people don't work well together they make bad decisions</b>.
<div class="author">-Kate Matsudaira</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
To change the architecture of a software-intensive system ensconced in a large organization, you often have to change the architecture of the organization. And ultimately, that is <b>a political problem, not just a technical one</b>.
<div class="author">-Grady Booch</div>
</div>

<h2 id="changing-role-of-architecture">Changing Role of Architecture</h2>

<div class="quote">
The role of architects has changed from trying to be the smartest person to <b>making everyone else smarter</b>.
<div class="author">-Gregor Hohpe</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
The architect's role is changing from being primarily a decision maker to being a coordinator, advisor, and knowledge manager ... <b>a central knowledge hub</b>.
<div class="author">-Rainer Weinreich &amp; Iris Groher</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
Rather than inject itself in every decision loop, <b>architecture should design mechanisms for teams to make better decisions</b> - they’ll know better anyhow, and slowing them down carries a high cost..
<div class="author">-Gregor Hohpe</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
Your architecture team’s job is to <b>solve your biggest problems</b>. The best setup is the one that allows it to accomplish that.
<div class="author">-Gregor Hohpe</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
Your organization has to <b>earn its way to an effective architecture function</b>. You can’t just plug some architects into the current mess and expect it to solve all your problems.
<div class="author">-Gregor Hophe</div>
</div>

<h2 id="complexity">Complexity</h2>

<div class="quote">
Excessive complexity is nature’s punishment for <b>organizations that are unable to make decisions.</b>
<div class="author">-Gregor Hohpe</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
<b>Metawork is more interesting than work</b>. ... we love complicated little puzzles to solve, so we keep overengineering everything.
<div class="author">-Neal Ford</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
Developers are <b>drawn to complexity like moths to a flame</b> often with the same result.
<div class="author">-Neal Ford</div>
</div>

<h2 id="other">Other</h2>

<div class="quote">
Architecture is just a collective hunch, a <b>shared hallucination</b>, an assertion by a set of stakeholders on the nature of their observable world, be it a world that is or a world as they wish it to be.
<div class="author">-Grady Booch</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
<b>Architects code</b>, but not to deliver code. Rather, to understand the ramifications of the decisions that they're making.
<div class="author">-Gregor Hohpe, Dave Farley</div>
</div>

<div class="quote">
Architectural decisions are design decisions that are <b>hard to make</b> or <b>costly to change</b>.
<div class="author">-Olaf Zimmermann</div>
</div>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My favorite quotes about architecture.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Context: Fast Moving Global Organizations</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/context" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Context: Fast Moving Global Organizations" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/context</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/context"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/roller-coaster-3605743_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/paulbr75-2938186/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=3605743">Paul Brennan</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=3605743">Pixabay</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong> Understand the context in which the ideas in this book developed.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>To better understand any idea or solution, it is crucial to understand the context in which these ideas developed.</li>
    <li>The grounded architecture approach has developed in the context of global, loosely coupled organizations that are diverse, with non-linear growth dynamics, and under transformation pressures.</li>
    <li>More specifically, the work I present here reflects my experiences as a Chief or Principal Architect at AVIV Group, eBay Classifieds, and Adevinta.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>
<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 130%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<p><br />
To better understand any idea or solution, it is crucial to understand the context in which these ideas developed. My approach to creating and running an architecture function is not an abstract idea. Instead, it is the generalization of many lessons learned while solving specific problems in a particular context.</p>

<div class="quote">
My approach to creating and running an architecture function is not an abstract idea. Instead, it is the generalization of many lessons learned while solving specific problems in a particular context.
</div>

<p>I base my ideas on my experiences as a Chief and Principal Architect at AVIV Group, eBay Classifieds, and Adevinta. In this section, I discuss critical characteristics of the organizational context that have had an impact on my definition of the grounded architecture approach:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>global scale</strong>: operating across multiple countries and continents with millions of users,</li>
  <li><strong>multi-dimensional diversity</strong>: the organizations I worked in were very diverse at all levels, including customer base, workforce, business models, team topologies, technology stacks,</li>
  <li><strong>nonlinear growth dynamics</strong>: in addition to organic growth, big organizations frequently change the portfolio both by mergers and acquisitions of new businesses and as well as by divestments,</li>
  <li><strong>synergies and transformation pressures</strong>: big organizations do not want just to be bing, they want to exploit the benefits of the economies of scale and reduce duplication of efforts,</li>
  <li><strong>decentralized, loosely-coupled organizational units</strong>: organizational units have significant autonomy.</li>
</ul>

<p>In the following sub-sections, I discuss these characteristics in more detail from an architectural viewpoint.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="characteristic-1-global-scale">Characteristic 1: Global Scale</h2>

<p>I was lucky to develop my approach in genuinely global and multicultural organizations. Global context leads to a massive scale:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Millions of daily user visits,</li>
  <li>Thousands of active software developers,</li>
  <li>Hundreds of product and development teams,</li>
  <li>Hundreds of millions of lines of source code, and</li>
  <li>Many geographies, cultures, and languages.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/earth-g217b5730b_1920.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/thedigitalartist-202249/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=2254769">Pete Linforth</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=2254769">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<p>The global scale introduces several compelling opportunities:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Increasing effectiveness: possibilities to reduce duplication of effort by centralizing shared activities.</li>
  <li>Leveraging economies of scale: achieving cost advantages, for instance, by reducing unit prices of used technologies.</li>
  <li>Increased business resilience and flexibility: possibility to compensate for negative local market changes with global resources.</li>
  <li>Bigger talent pool to support any local or global effort.</li>
  <li>Possibility for investments to support nonlinear growth by mergers and acquisitions (M&amp;As).</li>
</ul>

<p>The global and massive scale has many challenges:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Organizational complexity (e.g., thousands of possible communication channels).</li>
  <li>Complex technology landscape (e.g., many services and interconnections).</li>
  <li>Continuously high costs of workforce.</li>
  <li>Continuously high cost of computing resources.</li>
  <li>Complexity of running operations with high customer demands.</li>
  <li>Huge attack surface, many points on the boundary of our systems where an attacker can try to enter, cause an effect on, or extract data.</li>
  <li>Limitations of any manual process, such as diagram drawing, to create an overview of the organizational or technology landscape.</li>
</ul>

<p>Balancing opportunities and challenges on a global scale is one of the most challenging and rewarding aspects of my architectural work.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="characteristic-2-multi-dimensional-diversity">Characteristic 2: Multi-Dimensional Diversity</h2>

<p>The organizations I worked on were very diverse across several dimensions:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Diversity of cultures, both in terms of workforce and customers,</li>
  <li>Organizational diversity, with different sizes, complexity, and styles,</li>
  <li>Product diversity, covering many markets and customer segments,</li>
  <li>Architecture diversity, with legacy and modern approaches mixed together,</li>
  <li>Technology diversity at all levels.</li>
</ul>

<p>The global and multicultural nature of our context leads to diversity and multiple levels:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Diversity of decision-making styles</li>
  <li>Diversity of organizational styles and hierarchies</li>
  <li>Diversity of meeting styles</li>
  <li>Diversity of ways of dealing with feedback</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/pictures-g139ff7ebb_1280.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/simon-3/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=381937">Simon</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=381937">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<p>The organizations have many units, such as marketplaces (each with its sub-structures), global capabilities, enterprise IT teams, data capabilities, and generic IT infrastructure. In addition to their loose coupling, these organizational units differed in multiple ways:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Size: for instance, some units had hundreds of developers, and some units had only a dozen.</li>
  <li>Team topologies: some organizations had one team, while other teams were organized hierarchically.</li>
  <li>Position of architecture: with some organizations having local architecture teams and local lead architects, smaller units have their team members conducting architecture activities in addition to other responsibilities</li>
</ul>

<p>We had many architectural styles in active production systems, ranging from legacy monolith applications to complex modern Microservices and serverless ecosystems. Each part of the organization has a different history and a different legacy.</p>

<p>The primary technical infrastructure included several public cloud providers (AWS, GCP, Azure) and custom-built private data centers.</p>

<p>The systems also employed diverse application technologies, such as:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Database technologies (e.g., MySQL, Postgress, MongoDB, Cassandra, AWS RDS…).</li>
  <li>Backend programming languages (e.g., Java, C#, Go, Scala, PHP, Node.js, Kotlin…).</li>
  <li>Mobile app programming languages (e.g., Swift, Objective-C, Java, Kotlin, Flutter/Dart…).</li>
  <li>Frontend programming languages and frameworks (e.g., React, Android, AndroidJS, Vue, jQuery…).</li>
</ul>

<p>From an architectural perspective, diversity offers several opportunities:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Increasing innovation due to a diverse workforce and possibilities to creatively explore more technologies and tools.</li>
  <li>Addressing specific needs better by choosing from a more extensive and diverse pool of resources.</li>
</ul>

<p>Diversity also poses several challenges:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Increasing complexity and cognitive load of teams.</li>
  <li>Limited flexibility and reorganization possibilities as expertise is split among many domains and technologies.</li>
  <li>Higher technical debt due to many legacy components in many (outdated) technologies.</li>
</ul>

<p>From an architectural perspective, diversity is an excellent source of new possibilities but comes with challenges in controlling complexity.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="characteristic-3-nonlinear-growth-dynamics">Characteristic 3: Nonlinear Growth Dynamics</h2>

<p>Complex organizations like the one I have worked in are frequently very dynamic. Such organizations grow (or shrink) and reorganize often and significantly. They change both organically and inorganically. Organic growth is internal growth the company sees from its operations. Inorganic change comes from buying other businesses, opening new locations, or divesting.</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/blur-g6bc6ee2cc_1920.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/pexels-2286921/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1853262">Pexels</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1853262">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<p>Possibilities for nonlinear growth may be helpful in several scenarios:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Faster growth due to acquisitions of market segments.</li>
  <li>Speeding up innovation due to the acquisition of new technologies or services.</li>
</ul>

<p>Nonlinear dynamics have several influences on architectural activities:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Increased complexity due to many new organizational units.</li>
  <li>Increased complexity due to more diverse organization, process, and technologies, increased by every acquisition.</li>
  <li>More complex architecture to stay flexible if the organization decides to divest a part of the organization.</li>
</ul>

<p>Non-linear growth dynamics open up many challenges as they can lead to many surprises. And in business of IT 
<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/good-surprises-business-clemens-rettich/">there are no good surprises</a>.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="characteristic-4-synergy-and-transformation-pressures">Characteristic 4: Synergy and Transformation Pressures</h2>

<p>Complex organizations do not just grow. Instead, they want to be more efficient and leverage economies of scale, cost synergies, or increase capacity for innovation. Our investors expect us to transform to be more than a sum of our original parts.</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/gears-g06fe4e9a5_1920.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/mustangjoe-2162920/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1236578">MustangJoe</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1236578">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<p>Pressure for synergies and transformations can provide several opportunities:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Cost reductions.</li>
  <li>Acceleration due to more resources available when synergies happen.</li>
  <li>Innovation through more capacity and possibility for reuse and sharing.</li>
  <li>Faster scaling up of operations due to more efficiencies and lower unit costs.</li>
</ul>

<p>Pressure to be more synergic and efficient has its challenges:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Up-front investment is needed to gain any benefit.</li>
  <li>Such investment typically brings high risks.</li>
  <li>Productivity of some teams may (temporarily) drop due to the need to split effort between transformation activities and other work.</li>
  <li>After transformations, the complexity of the organization and technology landscape may increase due to more dependencies, e.g., reusing central services.</li>
</ul>

<p>Synergies and transformation pressures can lead to high expectations and pressure that complicate regular architecture work. On the positive side, such forces can create many new opportunities.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<h2 id="characteristic-5-decentralization-and-loose-coupling">Characteristic 5: Decentralization and Loose Coupling</h2>

<p>Researcher Karl Weick developed the concepts of tight and loose coupling to describe the organizational structure first in educational institutions and later applied to diverse businesses. According to Weick, a tightly coupled organization has mutually understood rules enforced by <em>inspection and feedback</em> systems. In tightly coupled organizations, management can more directly coordinate different departments’ activities according to a central strategy.</p>

<p>In a loosely coupled organization, some of the elements of a tightly coupled organization are absent. Employees have more autonomy, and different departments may operate with little coordination.</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/world-trade-center-g707209d17_1920.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/shire777-19410672/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=5889199">Shire777</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=5889199">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<p>Due to historical and strategic reasons, most organizational units I worked with were loosely coupled. Our companies frequently grow through acquisitions of companies in different marketplaces. The strategies also continually promoted a more independent evolution of each marketplace to better and faster address local market needs. Marketplaces often have a high level of autonomy, frequently with their development teams and sometimes with local C(P)TOs, CFOs, CMOs, or CEOs.</p>

<p>Loose coupling offers several advantages:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Higher flexibility: units can keep developing independently, addressing specific needs without synchronizing with other marketplaces.</li>
  <li>High development speed / faster time-to-market: fewer dependencies make it much easier for marketplaces to change and evolve their products for local needs.</li>
  <li>Innovation: possibilities to quickly explore ideas in smaller contexts.</li>
</ul>

<p>Loose coupling also has several challenges:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Duplication of effort: while local market needs differ, there is frequently a significant overlap in product features and technology. This overlap leads to duplication of effort as each marketplace creates solutions for the same problems.</li>
  <li>Increased accidental diversity: limited synchronization offers flexibility but may lead to significantly different design choices, making it challenging to consolidate solutions, move people between teams, or benefit from the economy of scale.</li>
  <li>Limited possibilities for central control: due to fewer dependencies and different goals, it is more difficult to introduce changes across the portfolio.</li>
</ul>

<p>Loose coupling is architecture-wise an interesting challenge as it frequently leads to a conflict between global alignment and control and local autonomy.</p>

<h2 id="questions-to-consider">Questions to Consider</h2>

<p>To better understand any idea or solution, it is crucial to understand the context in which these ideas developed. The same applies to applying concepts: contextualizing them in your organizations. When using ideas from this book, ask yourself how your organizational context differs from mine:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>What are the unique characteristics of your organizational context?</em></li>
  <li><em>What is the scale of your organization? How it affects architecture function?</em></li>
  <li><em>How diverse is your organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>What are grow dynamics of your organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>Are you experiencing synergy and transformation pressures?</em></li>
  <li><em>How (de)centralized is your organization?</em></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The grounded architecture approach has developed in the context of global, loosely coupled organizations that are diverse, with non-linear growth dynamics, and under transformation pressures. The work I present here reflects my experiences as a Chief or Principal Architect at AVIV Group, eBay Classifieds, and Adevinta.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/goals" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goals" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/requirements</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/goals"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/stress-gc7a712a2f_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/geralt-9301/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=7446584">Gerd Altmann</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=7446584">Pixabay</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong> Understand the requirements I identified for an architecture function in complex organizations.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>I identified the following needs that an architecture function should support: Executing At Scale, Increasing the Quality of Decision-Making with Data, Maximizing Organizational Alignment &amp; Learning, Higher Adaptivity.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>
<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 130%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<p><br />
Considering the scale and complexity of the organizational context I operated in, it was apparent that conventional approaches of doing architecture that rely on manual processes need to be revised.</p>
<div class="quote">
Considering the scale and complexity of the organizational context I operated in, it was apparent that conventional approaches of doing architecture that rely on manual processes need to be revised.
</div>

<p>More specifically, I identified the following needs that an architecture function should support.</p>

<h3 id="goal-1-executing-at-scale">Goal 1: Executing At Scale</h3>

<p>We needed to find a way to support hundreds of teams, and thousands of projects, with significant complexity and diversity.</p>

<h3 id="goal-2-increasing-quality-of-decisions-with-data">Goal 2: Increasing Quality of Decisions with Data</h3>

<p>Intuition does not work at scale. We need tools and mechanisms to make a decision process more data-informed and less dependent on opinions.</p>

<h3 id="goal-3-maximizing-organizational-alignment">Goal 3: Maximizing Organizational Alignment</h3>

<p>In a global, diverse, fast-moving organization, misalignment is a natural state. The architecture function should be a cohesive factor in minimizing such misalignments.</p>

<h3 id="goal-4-maximizing-organizational-learning">Goal 4: Maximizing Organizational Learning</h3>

<p>In complex organizations with lots of effort needed to maintain legacy systems, learning and following new technology developments takes work. Architecture should help organizations to learn fast, stay up-to-date with emerging technologies and industry trends and recommend technology upgrades.</p>

<h3 id="goal-5-adaptivity">Goal 5: Adaptivity</h3>

<p>Significant organic and inorganic changes are frequent and expected. The architecture function must adapt quickly to stay relevant in a new context.</p>

<h2 id="questions-to-consider">Questions to Consider</h2>

<p>Knowing what goals architecture practice needs to support in your organization is crucial to define structures and measuring your impact. Some of the plans may be universally applicable. Others may be unique to your context. Ask yourself the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>What is the scale of your architecture operations? Does your scale require special measures to ensure your architecture practice efficient operations?</em></li>
  <li><em>What are the key decisions you need to make? Do you have the data to base your decisions?</em></li>
  <li><em>How aligned are units in your organizations? How much friction is there? How can architecture function help?</em></li>
  <li><em>How much is your organization learning? How is the learning supported?</em></li>
  <li><em>How stable is your organization? How likely is it that significant changes will occur in your organization?</em></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I identified the following needs that an architecture function should support: Executing At Scale, Increasing the Quality of Decision-Making with Data, Maximizing Organizational Alignment & Learning, Higher Adaptivity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grounded Architecture: Introduction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/grounded-architecture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grounded Architecture: Introduction" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/grounded-architecture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/grounded-architecture"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/buildings-205986_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/ichigo121212-11728/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=205986">Ichigo121212</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=205986">Pixabay</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong> Get an overview of the Grounded Architecture structure: Data Pillar, People Pillar, and Architecture Activities Platform.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>I introduce three elements of Grounded Architecture: The Data Pillar, The People Pillar, The Architecture Activities Platform.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>
<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 130%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<p><br />
In this part of my playbook, I will introduce the structure of Grounded Architecture. I chose the term “Grounded Architecture” to highlight that the primary goal of my approach is to avoid having an “ivory tower” architecture function disconnected from the organization, which in a <a href="context">fast-moving, global, and diverse setting</a> is a real danger. In other words, I wanted to create an architectural function that is well-grounded in the organization.</p>

<div class="quote">
I chose the term "Grounded Architecture" to highlight that the primary goal of my approach is to avoid having an "ivory tower" architecture function disconnected from the organization. I wanted to create an architectural function that is well-grounded in the organization.
</div>

<p>Grounded Architecture has three elements:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The Data Pillar,</li>
  <li>The People Pillar,</li>
  <li>The Architecture Activities Platform.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/images/model.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The <em>Data Pillar</em> is a collection of tools and resources that enables architects to make data-informed decisions based on a real-time and complete overview of the organization’s technology landscape. The <a href="data">Data Pillar section</a> provides more details.</p>

<p>The <em>People Pillar</em> is a network of people doing architecture across the organization. This Pillar is crucial to ensure that architecture function has any tangible impact. As noted by Gregor Hohpe, to transform an organization, you do not need to solve mathematical equations; you need to move people. The <a href="people">People Pillar section</a> provides more details.</p>

<p>Lastly, the <em>Architecture Activities Platform</em> defines a set of processes and agreements enabling architects to do everything that architecture typically does, leveraging data and people pillars to create a data-informed, organization-wide impact. The <a href="activities-platform">Architecture Activites Platform section</a> provides more details on Technology Architecture Activities Platform. While the Architecture Activities Platform looks most like a typical architecture function, I consider such a platform only valid with the healthy Data and People pillars. Without data and people connections, an Architecture Activities Platform becomes an ivory tower institution, generating opinion-based decisions disconnected from reality.</p>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I introduce three elements of Grounded Architecture: The Data Pillar, The People Pillar, The Architecture Activities Platform.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Pillar</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Pillar" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/data-platform</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/data"><![CDATA[<p><img src="assets/images/arch/architecture-1857175_1920.jpg" style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/3844328-3844328/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1857175">Lorenzo Cafaro</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1857175">Pixabay</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong>  Understand how to use diverse data sources to support architecture decision-making processes and get concrete tips on creating architecture-centric data tools.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>The architecture data pillar serves as a medium to create a complete, up-to-date picture of critical elements of technology landscapes of big organizations.</li>
    <li>The data pillar provides an architecture-centric view on data about a technology landscape based on source code analyses, public cloud billing reports, vibrancy reports, or incident tickets.</li>
    <li>To facilitate creation of data pillars, I have been working on creating open-source tools, such as <a href="https://sokrates.dev">Sokrates</a>, that can help obtain valuable architectural insights from data sources, such as source code repositories.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>
<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 140%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<p><br />
In every place I worked on creating architectural functions, I strongly emphasized data. In the past several years, I have been working on creating open-source tools, such as <a href="https://sokrates.dev">Sokrates</a>, that can help obtain valuable architectural insights from data sources, such as source code repositories or public cloud billing reports. Consequently, one of the first steps I make in any architecture role is to create an architecture data pillar to get a complete, up-to-date picture of critical elements of the technology landscapes of an organization. Manual documentation does not scale in <a href="context">our context</a>, and relying on data ensures reliability and scalability.</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/model-data.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The good news is that big organizations have lots of data that, if used wisely, can provide an excellent basis for an architectural data pillar. With some automation and curation, getting a good overview of the technology landscape may be closer than it initially appears.</p>

<div class="quote">
 Manual documentation does not scale, and relying on data ensures reliability and scalability.
</div>

<h2 id="examples-of-data-sources-and-tools">Examples of Data Sources and Tools</h2>

<p>I’ve always aimed to get reliable data about technology with as much as possible automation. Some examples of data I used include:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Source code</strong>, which contains an incredible amount of information about technology, people’s activity, team dependencies, and the quality of software systems.</li>
  <li><strong>Public cloud billing reports</strong>, which provide an overview and trends used cloud services, regions, and budgets.</li>
  <li><strong>Incident reports</strong>, which can reveal trends and dependencies among incidents.</li>
  <li><strong>Key business metrics</strong>, like vibrancy, which can show user activity on our systems.</li>
  <li><strong>Messaging and collaboration platform (such as Slack) activity reports</strong>, which can help understand discussion topics and team interactions.</li>
</ul>

<p>In the following sections, I detail several of these architectural data-driven tools.</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/apps.png" style="padding: 4px; padding-top: 8px; padding-bottom: 8px; box-shadow: rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.16) 0px 1px 4px; margin-bottom: 6px" />
<br /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>A screenshot of the start page of the architecture data dashboard we’ve built and used at AVIV Group.</em></p>

<p><br /></p>
<h3 id="example-1-source-code-and-commit-history">Example 1: Source Code and Commit History</h3>

<p>I have repeatably found the source code to be an incredible source for creating data-driven architecture documentation. Source code and its commit history include an astonishing amount of information about technology, people activity, team dependencies, and the quality of software systems. I’ve started and still actively maintain the project <a href="https://sokrates.dev">Sokrates</a>, with the idea to help further extract data from source code that can help my work as an architect. I use Sokrates daily, improving it on the way.</p>

<div class="quote">
Source code and its commit history include an astonishing amount of information about technology, people activity, team dependencies, and the quality of software systems.
</div>

<p>I have designed Sokrates from an architect’s point of view, enabling quick zooming in and out into source code landscapes. On the one hand, Sokrates provides a high-level view of the landscape, summarizing data from all teams and groups. At the same time, you can zoom in on the details of particular systems to the code level. That means you can use the same tools to have CTO-level discussions looking at overall trends in our technology usage and costs. At the same time, I could engage with developers and discuss concrete code fragments and potential improvements in the code level (e.g., duplicated blocks, complex units, dependencies).</p>

<p>The Appendix at the end of this section shows some insights from source code analyses with Sokrates. For more complex examples of insights that Sokrates generates from source code, take a look at <a href="https://www.sokrates.dev/">Sokrates examples</a>, with analysis of complex open-source landscapes, such as:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://d3axxy9bcycpv7.cloudfront.net/asf/_sokrates_landscape/index.html"><strong>Apache Software Foundation Repositories</strong></a>, with aggregated multi-level analysis of more than 1,000 repositories with more than 180 million lines of code, more than 22,000 historical contributors, and 2.4 million commits.</li>
  <li><a href="https://d3axxy9bcycpv7.cloudfront.net/meta/_sokrates_landscape/index.html"><strong>Facebook/Meta OSS Repositories</strong></a>, with aggregated multi-level analysis of around 800 repositories with 120 million lines of code, more than 20,000 historical contributors, and more than 2 million commits.</li>
  <li><a href="https://d3axxy9bcycpv7.cloudfront.net/microsoft/_sokrates_landscape/index.html"><strong>Microsoft OSS Repositories</strong></a>, with aggregated multi-level analysis of more than 2,400 repositories with more than 100 million lines of code, more than 18,000 historical contributors, and more than 1.2 million commits.</li>
  <li><a href="https://d3axxy9bcycpv7.cloudfront.net/google/_sokrates_landscape/index.html"><strong>Google OSS Repositories</strong></a>, with aggregated multi-level analysis of more than 1,600 repositories with more than 200 million lines of code, more than 27,000 historical contributors, and more than 2.4 million commits.</li>
  <li><a href="https://d3axxy9bcycpv7.cloudfront.net/asf/_sokrates_landscape/index.html"><strong>Linux Source Code</strong></a>, with aggregated multi-level analysis of 178 Linux repository sub-folders with more than 23 million lines of code, more than 17,000 historical contributors, and more than 1.7 million commits.</li>
  <li><a href="https://d3axxy9bcycpv7.cloudfront.net/amzn/_sokrates_landscape/index.html"><strong>Amazon OSS Repositories</strong></a>, with aggregated multi-level analysis of more than 2,700 repositories with more than 130 million lines of code, more than 13,000 historical contributors, and more than 600,000 commits.</li>
</ul>

<p>In addition to standard source code and commit history analyses, I also have built several special source code analyses to get further details:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Travis and Jenkins files analyzers to understand how teams build CI/CD pipelines.</li>
  <li>Dockerfile scan to create a tech radar of runtime technologies.</li>
  <li>GitHub API pull requests analyses to identify deployment frequency.</li>
</ul>

<p>And I encourage you to experiment with your source-code analyses.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h3 id="example-2-public-cloud-usage">Example 2: Public Cloud Usage</h3>

<p>Migrating to the public cloud can dramatically increase transparency thanks to uniform automation and monitoring. The public cloud transparency offers an incredible amount of valuable data out-of-box.</p>

<p>Figure 1 shows the anonymous screenshot of the Cloud usage explorer, a tool I built to visualize automatically-collected data from standard Google Cloud Platform (GCP) usage reports.</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/archdata/cloud-usage-explorer.png" alt="" />
<br />
<em><strong>Figure 1:</strong> An example of a cloud usage explorer.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com">Amazon Web Services (AWS)</a>, <a href="https://cloud.google.com/">Google Cloud Platform (GCP)</a>, <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/">Microsoft Azure</a>, and other Public Cloud Providers give detailed data about which platform uses which services, resource family, and budget. You can also understand which people and teams have access to each service. It is possible to get real-time information about cloud usage and understand the trends fully automatically.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h3 id="example-3-financial-and-vibrancy-data">Example 3: Financial and Vibrancy Data</h3>

<p>Finance departments are very data-driven and have high-quality data that could be relevant for architects. In addition to standard costs, budgets, and other pure financial data types, I frequently found that finance teams also have different data sources, such as vibrancy or usage levels. These teams need such data to, for instance, correlate finance performance with usage levels. Such usage data are beneficial for architecture discussions. For example, linking usage levels and vibrancy of systems with their public cloud usage can identify areas of improvement and inefficiencies.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="using-architecture-data-pillar">Using Architecture Data Pillar</h2>

<p>The architecture data pillar can provide lots of data. Sometimes, as in an ordinary map or atlas, such data could be helpful for those who want to orient themselves and understand the context. But you could obtain more insights from such data. However, finding the right ways to interpret and use data requires active effort. In other words, the data can give you the answers, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/42_(number)#The_Hitchhiker's_Guide_to_the_Galaxy">we may not know the questions</a>. Here are some of the questions you can ask when you have data:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Are we aligned and going in the same direction? Source code overviews, public cloud usage explorers, or tech radars can highlight differences among systems and teams and trigger discussions.</li>
  <li>Are we using technology optimally? Comparing usage trends between teams can show interesting outliners (both positive and negative).</li>
  <li>Are there indicators of poor code quality? Too large systems, duplication, long units, or long files.</li>
  <li>Productivity: is more really more or is more actually less. For instance, comparing the number of git merges with the number of developers can indicate if our dev processes are scalable. When we scale up teams, we want to speed up our delivery (but if team structure is not proper, it can easily be the opposite as people “step on each other toes”).</li>
  <li>Do we collaborate in the way we want? Repository analysis can point out team topologies and (un)desired dependencies.</li>
  <li>Do we work on the things we want? We may want to focus more on innovations, but in reality, we may spend too much time on legacy maintenance.</li>
</ul>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="building-data-pillar">Building Data Pillar</h2>

<p>While each organization will have its unique sets of data, here are some tips I found helpful in my approach to forming the architecture data pillar:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Start with the source code</strong>. My motto is “Talk is expensive. Show me the code.” I scan as soon as possible all source code using tools such as <a href="https://sokrates.dev">Sokrates</a>. I highly recommend <a href="https://sokrates.dev">Sokrates</a> as the basis for the data pillar, but other simple analyses could also provide a good starting point. Modern IT enterprises store almost everything as a code. It is the richest and most up-to-date documentation on most things happening in an IT enterprise.</li>
  <li><strong>Connect with finance and governance teams</strong> to get exports of their data (without sensitive parts, such as revenue projections). Cloud billing reports and data about vibrancy or revenue streams are collected anyway. By extracting more technology-oriented data (e.g., public cloud technology usage trends) and connecting them to other data, many new insights may be obtained without starting new processes or asking people to provide more details. First, leverage what you have, squeeze all the value from it, then ask people for any missing elements.</li>
  <li><strong>Use simple and easy-to-maintain infrastructures</strong>. For example, I publish the results of Sokrates analyses and other simple data Web apps as static resources in our enterprise GithHub pages. Configuring more complex infrastructure with complex databases and backend software requires more maintenance.</li>
  <li><strong>Maintain a culture of transparency</strong>. It is much simpler a more effective to share fewer data with everyone than to have more data, but complex authorization is needed.</li>
  <li><strong>Own the curation</strong>. People need to be able to trust your data. Spend enough time to understand data sets, curate them, and ensure presentation consistency. I am a master curator and chief UX designer of a data pillar.</li>
  <li><strong>Build maps, not control units</strong>. The main inspiration for my work is map-making. As noted by Brené Brown, maps are one of the most critical documents in human history (see <a href="https://brenebrown.com/book/atlas-of-the-heart/">Atlas of the Heart</a> for a discussion on a mapmaking metaphor). They give us tools to store and exchange knowledge about space and place. While there are differences between maps and the layers they show, the one thing that all maps do is provide readers with orientation. A sense of place is central to meaning-making. Maps are also composed of multiple layers. Similarly, the architecture data pillar offers data layers about systems, describing their size, connections, quality, security, or human activity.</li>
</ul>

<p>While I do not want to prescribe the best technology, I can tell what I use in daily work. I build most architecture data tools as simple web applications, taking data from JSON files hosted on a static web server. See some of <a href="https://obren.io/tools">my public tools</a> to illustrate how I build such simple data-driven web apps.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="appendix-examples-of-insights-from-source-code-analyses-with-sokrates">Appendix: Examples of Insights From Source Code Analyses with Sokrates</h2>

<p>Figures 3 to 7 show some insights from source code analyses with Sokrates.</p>

<p><br />
<img src="assets/images/archdata/src_1.png" alt="" />
<strong>Figure 3</strong>: <em>Sokrates can instantly create a helicopter view of the technology landscape, programming languages, active contributors, and commit trends.</em>
<br />
<br /></p>

<p><img src="assets/images/archdata/src_2.png" alt="" />
<strong>Figure 4</strong>: <em>Sokrates can show detailed code and contributors’ trends per repository, enabling zooming in each repository up to the code level.</em>
<br />
<br /></p>

<p><img src="assets/images/archdata/src_5.png" alt="" />
<strong>Figure 5</strong>: <em>Sokrates can create a tech radar by tagging projects with identified technologies.</em>
<br />
<br /></p>

<p><img src="assets/images/archdata/src_3.png" alt="" />
<strong>Figure 6</strong>: <em>Sokrates can show contributor trends, distribution of “veterans” and “rookies,” and dependencies between people and repositories, enabling zooming in into patterns of the contribution of individual contributors.</em>
<br />
<br /></p>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/sokrates_teams.png" alt="" />
<strong>Figure 7</strong>: <em>Sokrates can reveal the team topologies by plotting 2D and 3D graphs of dependencies that people create through working on the same repositories in the same period.</em>
<br />
<br /></p>

<h2 id="questions-to-consider">Questions to Consider</h2>

<p>Using data can significantly improve the efficiency and impact of architectural practice. But there are no simple tools that can instantly provide you insights. Ask yourself the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Have you considered using open-source tools like Sokrates to gain architectural insights from data sources? Why or why not?</em></li>
  <li><em>What are your views on the reliability and scalability of manual documentation as opposed to data reliance?</em></li>
  <li><em>What steps would you take to create an architecture data pillar in your organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>Do you think there are untapped data sources within your organization that could inform your architectural data pillar?</em></li>
  <li><em>How could you automate the process of gathering data for architectural insights in your organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>What examples can you provide of the data you’ve used to gain reliable information about technology in your organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>How would you examine public cloud billing reports, incident reports, or key business metrics for architectural insights?</em></li>
  <li><em>How can you ensure your data is reliable and up-to-date?</em></li>
  <li><em>Do you collaborate with finance and governance teams to incorporate financial and vibrancy data into your data analysis?</em></li>
  <li><em>Is there a culture of transparency in your organization?</em></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The architecture data pillar serves as a medium to create a complete, up-to-date picture of critical elements of technology landscapes of big organizations. The platform provides an architecture-centric view on data about a technology landscape based on source code analyses, public cloud billing reports, vibrancy reports, or incident tickets.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">People Pillar</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/people" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="People Pillar" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/people</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/people"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/construction-4939383_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/mostafa_meraji-13551092/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=4939383">mostafa meraji</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=4939383">Pixabay</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong>  Understand that architecture practice is all about people and get tips on creating organizational structures that support practical architecture functions.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>Developing the architecture function requires having competent, empowered, and motivated architects.</li>
    <li>Any architecture function must carefully organize, empower,
  and leverage scarce architecture talent.</li>
    <li>We should not take architectural talent for granted. Architects are bridging local business, product, 
  organizational, and technology issues. Architects are difficult to hire talent as they need not only 
  in-depth technical knowledge but also domain-specific and organizational knowledge.</li>
    <li>In my work in the past few years, I was working by combining, in different forms, two teams of architects: a small
central architecture team and a cross-organizational distributed virtual team.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 140%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<p><br /></p>

<p>The <strong>People Pillar</strong> is an essential element of Grounded Architecture. As noted by Gregor Hohpe, to transform an
organization, you do not need to solve mathematical equations. You need to move people. Consequently, having a strong
network of people doing architecture across the organization is crucial to ensure that the architecture function has any
tangible impact. In other words, Strong Architecture =
Strong Architects.</p>

<div class="quote">
Strong Architecture = Strong Architects.
</div>

<p>Developing the architecture function requires having competent, empowered, and motivated architects. We should not take
architectural talent for granted. Architects are bridging local business, product, organizational, and technology
issues. Architects are difficult to hire talent as they need not only in-depth technical knowledge but also
domain-specific and organizational knowledge. Consequently, any architecture function must carefully organize, empower,
and leverage scarce architecture talent.</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/model-people.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>In my work in the past few years, I was working by combining, in different forms, two teams of architects: a small
central architecture team and a cross-organizational distributed virtual team. A central architecture team is an enabler
for the rest of the organization, supporting teams and addressing global strategic topics. A distributed virtual
architecture team consists of architects (or other people making architecture decisions in their teams) working in local
organizational units but spending some time in a virtual team with peers from other teams. Such a distributed virtual
architecture team is a crucial element of an architecture function. It provides the connection (grounding) across all
parts and levels of the organization, increasing transparency, building people networks, and making it easier to
implement change.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="background-central-andor-federated-architecture-function">Background: Central and/or Federated Architecture Function</h2>

<p>The architecture function generally follows one of two fundamental models: central or federated.
(<a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/business-functions/mckinsey-digital/our-insights/tech-forward/crafting-the-optimal-model-for-the-it-architecture-organization">McKinsey 2022</a>).</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/arch_teams.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The central model involves a large-scale central architecture team. The central team typically defines the process for
approval of new work and assures adherence by development teams. In this model, development teams have few or no
qualified solution architects that are typically a part of the central architecture team. This model also holds
centralized infrastructure, operations, and security teams apart from the development function. Control and governance
are typically the primary concerns of the central architecture team.</p>

<p>The federated model generally relies upon a guild or “community of practice” of solution architects embedded into
individual development teams. A small central architecture team or an architecture center of excellence (CoE) may
complement such a guild. The federated model’s architects facilitate high-level planning and act as on-demand service
providers for distributed teams.</p>

<p>The federated model is more commonly associated with cross-functional DevOps culture. The roles of solution and
enterprise architects are generally broader in scope to integrate infrastructure, operations, and security concerns in
product-oriented teams. The architect’s role focuses on facilitation and enablement rather than control.</p>

<p>Today, modern agile organizations mainly adopt the federated model. This approach increases the likelihood that the
central architecture team will spend time closely involved with the challenges identified in the teams. The model
ensures that the architects will be evaluated against the goals of the individual products they support, thereby
focusing on improving performance and reducing complexity.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="the-hybrid-model">The Hybrid Model</h2>

<p>To operate in a complex <a href="context">context</a>, you need to invested effort to ensure we have the right people at the right
places. In the end, I usually found it best to adopted model of a hybrid organization combining elements of central and
federated orientation structures:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A Small Scale Central Architectural Teams, and</li>
  <li>Architecture Guilds &amp; Virtual Architectural Teams.</li>
</ul>

<p>The hybrid team structure supports well our <a href="goals">goals</a> of executing at scale. Guilds and virtual architecture teams
support execution by increasing the number of people involved in architectural activities and increasing work efficiency
through better alignment. By having members representing various organizational units, we are able to have much more
impact across the board. And having some capacity on the central level serves as a catalyst helping people at local
levels to do their job while being aligned and better connected with overall strategic goals and other teams working on
similar topics.</p>

<h3 id="central-architecture-team">Central Architecture Team</h3>

<p>The roles of people in central teams may differ depending on the organization. In addition to doing typical architecture
work, I found it helpful to be able to have people that can cover the following types of responsibilities:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Build and maintain the architecture <a href="data">Data Pillar</a>.</strong> Building a data pillar will not happen by
accident. It requires clear ownership, curation, and technical support.</li>
  <li><strong>Promote data-informed decision-making.</strong> identify, collect, and use relevant data. Only some people are used to
applying data in their decision-making. Architects should provide support and be a role-model for data-informed
organizations.</li>
  <li><strong>Proactively identify, connect, and maintain relationships with all relevant stakeholders.</strong> Architects are
frequently uniquely positioned to bridge different organizational units and stakeholders.</li>
  <li><strong>Build internal architecture communities and guilds.</strong> Organizing rituals and people requires active effort.</li>
</ul>

<p>While guilds and virtual teams could do many of the listed activities, the voluntary nature of guilds and virtual groups
makes such support more fragile. The central architecture team can take full long-term ownership of some topics and be a
backup if community support weakens, ensuring long-term continuity.</p>

<h3 id="architecture-guilds--virtual-architecture-teams">Architecture Guilds &amp; Virtual Architecture Teams</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“A lot of cheap seats in the arena are filled with people who never venture onto the floor. They just hurl
mean-spirited criticisms and put-downs from a safe distance. … we need to be selective about the feedback we let into
our lives. For me, if you’re not in the arena getting your ass kicked, I’m not interested in your feedback.”</em> — Brené
Brown, Rising Strong</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I always found it essential to connect organization members passionate about architecture in some form, a guild, a
community of interest, or a virtual team.</p>

<p>Guild or virtual teams are composed of people that work full-time as architects or tech leads in specific organizational
units but spend part-time collaborating with architects from other departments to reach more alignment, share knowledge,
and leverage each other’s work. In this peer-to-peer community, architects are collectively responsible for identifying
and growing architectural talent, mentoring, and helping each other.</p>

<p>When having many guilds and teams, we have organized architects in several sub-areas:</p>

<ul>
  <li>General teams for a broader set of architectural topics.</li>
  <li>Specialist teams focus on a particular part of the technology stack. Examples include native mobile apps, web
frontends, public cloud infrastructure, etc.</li>
  <li>Strategic initiatives teams. For instance, data strategy, public cloud strategy, transactions, or verticalization.</li>
</ul>

<p>Having places and events to connect central and distributed teams is essential. Such events can transform individual
experiences into collective knowledge that can benefit the whole organization. In most organizations I worked in,
distributed teams followed a similar pattern of rituals:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Regular (e.g., bi-weekly) forums, with updates, announcements of architectural spikes, and sharing or architectural
decisions (similar to Andrew
Harmel-Law’s <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/scaling-architecture-conversationally.html">Advice Process</a>)</li>
  <li>Annual or bi-annual summit, with several days of intensive knowledge sharing and workshops</li>
  <li>Ad-hoc workshops focusing on some explicit topic</li>
</ul>

<p>While the central team can provide some essential support, all communities must take the initiative and engage as many
people as possible during these events. People should be active participants rather than passive receivers of
information to ensure more involvement and commitment.</p>

<h3 id="embracing-diverse-team-structures">Embracing Diverse Team Structures</h3>

<p>When building architecture guilds and virtual architecture teams, it is essential to acknowledge that organizational
units have very diverse structures and sizes. There is no one-fit-all solution about how departments should assign
architecture responsibilities. I generally worked on three types of team-architect systems per Gregor Hohpe’s view of
architects and their teams’ relationships (Figure 1). That means that some units have lead architects coordinating or
leading multiple teams. We often have cases where an architect was a full-time member of a team working on specific
products or other features. I also worked with teams that needed an architect but several senior developers making
architectural decisions.</p>

<p><img src="https://esilva.net/assets/team-architecture-topologies.png" alt="" />
<em><strong>Figure 1:</strong> A model for organizing (local) architects. Credit: <a href="https://architectelevator.com/architecture/organizing-architecture/">Gregor Hohpe</a>.</em></p>

<p>In big organization, embracing diversity is a pre-requirements to have any broad impact.</p>

<div class="quote">
In big organization, embracing diversity is a pre-requirements to have any broad impact.
</div>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="building-people-pillar">Building People Pillar</h2>

<p>While each organization will need its unique approach, here are some tips I found helpful in my approach to forming
architecture teams or “<a href="people">People Pillar</a>”:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Before making grandiose plans for reorganizations, connect with the people already doing architectural work in an
organization, creating a community of practices or a virtual team. Being inclusive and connecting all key tech
leaders, regardless of their actual position and title, is vital. Being well-connected to these people will be crucial
in any architecture organization, so you will always benefit from this effort.</li>
  <li>If creating a virtual team is a part of your architecture strategy, move away from making an informal community of
practice towards building a team with more accountability and responsibility. It was helpful to get buy-in from key
stakeholders, e.g., Engineering Leaders who should want to get their people to work together with other architects.</li>
  <li>Connect with as many non-architecture stakeholders as possible in the early stages. Again, being well-connected to
these stakeholders will be crucial in any architecture organization.</li>
  <li>Align the architecture vision with all stakeholders.</li>
  <li>Avoid hiring <a href="https://architectelevator.com/transformation/dont-hire-hitman/">digital hitman</a>. Invest in growing
internal talent. Architects require technology, domain, and organization knowledge. Finding such a person
outside the organization is challenging.</li>
  <li>Externalize. Reach out and connect. Participate in external events. Publish. Being strong externally can help you to
both grow and attract architectural talent.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/pyramid-g88f894074_1920.jpg" alt="" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/chantellev-2412495/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1336120">Chantellev</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1336120">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<h2 id="questions-to-consider">Questions to Consider</h2>

<p>It is difficult to overestimate the importance of people for architecture practice, yet many organizations take architectural talent for granted. To reflect on the importance of carefully organizing, empowering, and leveraging scarce architecture talent, ask yourself the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Reflect on your organization’s current architecture function. Do you have a strong network of architects across the organization? If not, what steps could you take to strengthen this?</em></li>
  <li><em>How do you ensure architects’ competency, empowerment, and motivation in your organization? What systems do you have in place to develop architectural talent?</em></li>
  <li><em>Which central, federated, or hybrid model best represents your current architectural function? Why was this model chosen, and how effective has it been for your organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>If you are part of a central architecture team, how would you support the rest of the organization? How would you contribute to the architecture function if you were part of a distributed virtual team?</em></li>
  <li><em>Consider having the roles of central architecture teams and federated architecture teams in your organization. How do they complement each other?</em></li>
  <li><em>How effective is the current division of responsibilities among architects in your organization? Are there areas of overlap or gaps in coverage?</em></li>
  <li><em>What steps has your organization taken to ensure architects are well-connected across all parts and levels? What impact has this had on transparency and the implementation of changes?</em></li>
  <li><em>Reflect on the diversity of team structures within your organization. How does this diversity impact the roles and responsibilities of architects?</em></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We should not take our architectural talent for granted. Architects are bridging local business, product, organizational, and technology issues. Architects are difficult to hire talent as they need in-depth technical knowledge and domain-specific and organizational knowledge. Therefore, we need to make sure to support, organize, and leverage architecture talent.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Architecture Activities Platform</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/activities-platform" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Architecture Activities Platform" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/activities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/activities-platform"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/parliament-366199_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/cocoparisienne-127419/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=366199">Anja</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=366199">Pixabay</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong>  Understand what activities you can do as a part of architecture practice and get tips on creating pragmatic operating models.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>The Architecture Activities Platform defines a set of processes and agreements enabling architects to do everything architecture typically does, leveraging data and people pillars to create a data-informed, organization-wide impact.</li>
    <li>Examples of activities include: supporting teams in their daily work; tracking tech debt, defining tech debt reduction programs; performing technical due diligence; standardization of processes and documentation; defining cloud, data, and platform strategies.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>
<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 140%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<p><br />
Each organization will have different architectural needs and contexts. When forming architecture functions, I use as a starting point these <a href="https://architectelevator.com/architecture/organizing-architecture/">two pieces of advice from Gregor Hohpe</a>:</p>
<ul>
  <li><em>“Your architecture team’s job is to solve your biggest problems. The best setup is the one that allows it to accomplish that.”</em></li>
  <li><em>“Your organization has to earn its way to an effective architecture function. You can’t just plug some architects into the current mess and expect it to solve all your problems.”</em></li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/images/model-strategy.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Considering the previous two points from Gregor Hohpe, there is no one-size-fits-all approach: each organization must find activities and operating models to enable architecture to work on the most critical problems.</p>

<div class="quote">
There is no one-size-fits-all approach: each organization must find activities and operating models to enable architecture to work on the most critical problems. 
</div>

<p>The Architecture Activities Platform is where we have to perform activities that help an organization reach its goals. The Architecture Activities Platform defines a set of processes and agreements enabling architects to do everything architecture typically does, leveraging data and people pillars to create a data-informed, organization-wide impact. In all these activities, data and people posts provide foundations for data-informed decision-making well-embedded in the organization.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="examples-of-architecture-activities">Examples of Architecture Activities</h2>

<p>Here are some examples of activities I have been performing with architects:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Design mechanisms for teams to make better decisions.</strong> This includes creating global decision-support mechanisms, such as <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/scaling-architecture-conversationally.html">advisory forums</a>, formal design authority (for compliance-sensitive projects), and team-specific mechanisms, such as escalation paths in case of decision conflicts (e.g., teams cannot align on a common messaging middleware).</li>
  <li><strong>Supporting teams in their daily work.</strong> Being part of key team activities, aligning architectural work with team rituals to provide timely support, and supporting the team in all crucial phases of their work (e.g., reviewing architecture proposals early before the project or sprint start).</li>
  <li><strong>Supporting planned new initiatives and projects.</strong> Ensuring alignment between projects that require multi-team collaboration.</li>
  <li><strong>Supporting teams in dealing with the legacy landscape.</strong> Providing data and knowledge regarding legacy landscape, identifying hotspots (e.g., frequently changed, low-quality untested pieces of legacy code), defining scenarios and roadmap for legacy modernization.</li>
  <li><strong>Tracking tech debt, defining tech debt reduction programs.</strong> Defining a centrally aligned backlog of technology depth, defining programs for its reduction and integration in planning processes.</li>
  <li><strong>Performing SWOT and other analyses of platforms and systems.</strong> Doing deep dives to better understand some areas of the technology landscape and create plans and roadmaps for improvement.</li>
  <li><strong>Standardization of processes and documentation</strong>. Defining common templates for documents such as Architectural Decision Records (ADRs), Technical Design Reviews (TDRs), or common diagrams.</li>
  <li><strong>Supporting merger and acquisitions (M&amp;A) activities with expertise and analyses.</strong> Support analyses, recommendations, and integration planning regarding mergers and acquisitions.</li>
  <li><strong>Defining key technology strategies.</strong> Examples include Cloud, Data, and Platform strategies.</li>
  <li><strong>Defining vision and direction of technology, frequently collaborating with Engineering Leaders.</strong> Working with managers to create a sustainable organizational setting aligned with technology strategies.</li>
</ul>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="operating-model">Operating Model</h2>

<p>While exact activities and their scope will depend on an organization setting and will change over time, I aimed to implement the common operational model in daily work.</p>

<p>Inspired by Gregor Hohpe’s strategy-principles-decisions model Figure 1 illustrates the process.</p>

<div>
<a href="assets/images/arch/architecture-system.png" target="_blank">
    <img src="assets/images/arch/architecture-system.png" />
</a>
</div>
<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>A common operating model I typically use for Grounded Architecture activities.</em></p>

<p>A common operating model I typically use for Grounded Architecture activities is as follows:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Architects engage with stakeholders and product and project teams in a <strong>collaborative and supportive manner</strong>.</li>
  <li>Architects are <strong>empowering the teams</strong> so that they make most of the decisions.</li>
  <li>In all activities, the architecture function and architects:
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Bring relevant data</strong> to inform decisions leveraging the <a href="data">Data Pillar</a>.</li>
      <li><strong>Define decision boundaries</strong> to enable the minimal level of compatibility and strategic alignment (e.g., public cloud provider, tech stack constraints).</li>
      <li><strong>Define key principles</strong> to facilitate consistency in decision-making.</li>
      <li><strong>Share and generalize</strong> lessons learned.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Architects then spend their time in <strong>constant motion</strong> between supporting teams’ <strong>daily work</strong> and working on <strong>strategic topics</strong>, helping the organization achieve alignment between strategy and implementation.</li>
</ul>

<div class="quote">
My goal was to avoid formal bureaucratic approval processes, where architects appear too late and are frequently busy approving trivial decisions.
</div>

<p>Another characteristic of this operating model is <strong>shifting left</strong> the architecture work. My goal was to avoid formal bureaucratic approval processes, where architects appear too late and are frequently busy approving trivial decisions. Instead, my goal was to have architects involved early in any of the processes, such as during the planning and preparation stages, where it is possible to make more significant changes.</p>

<h3 id="distributing-decisions">Distributing Decisions</h3>

<p>With proposed operating model, I aimed to keep architectural decision-making distributed across the organization and embedded in the development teams. Development teams traditionally have the best insights and most information relevant for making a decision.</p>

<div class="quote">
Grounded architecture aims to make relevant information more readily available to a broader audience and better connect people when making decisions.
</div>

<p>As noted by Gregor Hohpe, the worst case of organizational decision-making happens when people with relevant information are not allowed to make decisions, while people who lack sufficient information make all decisions. Grounded architecture aims to make relevant information more readily available to a broader audience and better connect people when making decisions.</p>

<h3 id="autonomy-and-alignment">Autonomy and Alignment</h3>

<p>While I aim to create a mechanism to give teams autonomy, autonomy does not mean that teams are alone and do not align with anyone, do not get feedback from anyone, and do whatever they want. Autonomy must be complemented with high transparency and proactivity in alignment with other teams.</p>

<p>I have sometimes implemented the concept of a <strong>decision pyramid</strong> to give maximal autonomy to the teams while maintaining a <strong>minimal</strong> level of global <strong>alignment and compatibility</strong> (Figure 2).</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/decision-pyramid.jpg" alt="" />
<em><strong>Figure 2:</strong> A decision pyramid. The development teams should make most decisions. However, several strategic and area-level decisions may provide decision boundaries for teams (e.g., a public cloud provider).</em></p>

<p>Development teams should make most of the decisions. However, several strategic and area-level choices may provide team decision boundaries. For example, selecting the public cloud provider is typically a CTO-level strategic decision. Similarly, engineering leaders may want to limit some choices, such as the number of programming languages, to more easily train new people, maintain code, and support moves between teams.</p>

<h2 id="questions-to-consider">Questions to Consider</h2>

<p>Your architecture practice job is to solve the biggest problems in your organization. Ask yourself the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>How can you identify the most critical problems that your architecture team needs to solve in your organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>What activities and operating models can you think of that will best enable architecture in your organization to work on these critical problems?</em></li>
  <li><em>In your organization, what does the Architecture Activities Platform look like, and how could it be improved?</em></li>
  <li><em>Which of the provided examples of architecture activities are you currently performing in your organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>How does the proposed common operating model align with your current operational practices in your organization? What changes might be necessary to adopt this model?</em></li>
  <li><em>In your experience, how early are architects involved in projects and activities? Do you agree with the goal of ‘shifting left’ the architecture work?</em></li>
  <li><em>How are architectural decisions distributed across your organization currently? How could this process be improved to ensure the people with the most relevant information make the decisions?</em></li>
  <li><em>Reflect on the balance of autonomy and alignment in your organization. How could you better implement a mechanism to give teams autonomy while maintaining alignment and compatibility with global strategy?</em></li>
  <li><em>How does the concept of a decision pyramid resonate with you? How is it reflected in your current organization, and how could it be better implemented?</em></li>
  <li><em>Which strategic and area-level decisions provide team decision boundaries in your organization? Are there areas where you need more or less limitations to optimize performance?</em></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Architecture Activities Platform is the place where, by leveraging data and people pillars, we performed activities that help an organization to reach it goals. Here are some examples: supporting teams in their daily work; tracking tech debt, defining tech debt reduction programs; performing technical due diligence; standardization of processes and documentation; defining cloud, data, and platform strategies.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Value of Grounded Architecture</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/value" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Value of Grounded Architecture" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/value</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/value"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/gold-gd9bc167a4_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/nl/users/mwewering-185784/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=2800315">Matthias Wewering</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com/nl//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=2800315">Pixabay</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong>  Understand the value that architecture practice based on the ideas of Grounded Architecture can create for an organization.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>When Grounded Architecture is in place, it can have a significant positive impact on the functioning of an organization.</li>
    <li>These categories of impact are: Executing At Scale, Increasing the Quality of Decision-Making with Data, Maximizing Organizational Alignment &amp; Learning, Higher Adaptivity.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>
<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 140%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<p><br />
When Grounded Architecture is in place, it can have a significant positive impact on the functioning of an organization:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Enable Execution of Architecture Function At Scale,</li>
  <li>Increase the Quality of Decision-Making with Data,</li>
  <li>Maximize Organizational Alignment,</li>
  <li>Maximize Organizational Learning, and</li>
  <li>Increase Architecture Function Adaptivity,</li>
</ul>

<p>The following sections elaborate on these categories in line with the <a href="goals">goals</a>.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="executing-at-scale">Executing at Scale</h2>

<p>Grounded Architecture aims to enable architecture functions to operate at scale efficiently. We must rely on something other than intuition and manual processes when supporting thousands of developers and dealing with hundreds of millions of lines of code.</p>

<p><br />
<img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/earth-g8ffaadaba_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/wikiimages-1897/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=11595">WikiImages</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=11595">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<p>The architecture data pillar aims to support working at scale with automation and self-service. Our People Pillar aims to help execution at scale by developing connections at all levels of the organization, increasing transparency, and through a strong network speeding up alignment and the execution of shared decisions.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="increasing-the-quality-of-decision-making-with-data">Increasing the Quality of Decision-Making with Data</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“If we have data, let’s look at data. If all we have are opinions, let’s go with mine.”</em> -— Jim Barksdale</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Architectural discussions can be very heated and opinionated. There are significant benefits to making our decision process as much as possible data-driven. It is one of the critical tasks for any architect to maintain high-quality data on relevant internal and external technology developments, providing fuel for data-informed discussions and decision-making.</p>

<p><br />
<img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/doors-gf67a9cff2_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/qimono-1962238/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1767563">Arek Socha</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=1767563">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<p>The Data Pillar enables architects to move away from opinion-based decisions to data-driven economic risk modeling to become more data-driven. Such frameworks can help architects to achieve the following (credit Gregor Hohpe):</p>
<ul>
  <li>dismantle the buzzwords, present the problem in clear terms, understandable to a broader audience</li>
  <li>identify the real drivers behind buzzwords based on internal and external research</li>
  <li>bring data into the discussion</li>
  <li>translate drivers into an economic risk model, and use the model and data to find the best spot for the given business context</li>
</ul>

<p><br />
<br /></p>

<h2 id="maximizing-organizational-alignment">Maximizing Organizational Alignment</h2>

<p>Misalignment frequently happens in big organizations. The <a href="data">Data Pillar</a> can increase organizational alignment by creating transparency. The <a href="people">People Pillar</a> develops global structures that can help people before and after they make an architectural decision:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Before people decide, people starting to work simultaneously on the same topics can decide to work together, minimize effort duplication, and in that way, save time and resources.</li>
  <li>After making a decision, Grounded Architecture can make all organizations aware of it and distribute it so everyone can profit from lessons learned in one unit.</li>
</ul>

<p><img style="width: 100%;" src="assets/images/Misalignment-1024x523.png" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://blog.crisp.se/2016/05/30/henrikkniberg/misalignment">Henrik Kniberg</a>
</div>
<p><br />
<br /></p>

<h2 id="maximizing-organizational-learning">Maximizing Organizational Learning</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Good judgment comes from experience, and experience comes from bad judgment.”</em> – Fred Brooks</p>

  <p><em>” I expect you to learn to be better each day. I challenge you to look at each working day as an opportunity to learn more, and by doing so, to grow as a person.”</em> – L. David Marquet</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When we have teams of well-connected architects and other stakeholders, such groups can transform individual experiences into collective knowledge to benefit the whole organization.</p>

<p>One of architects’ primary daily tasks is learning. We must discover new things about our domain, teams, tools, and technologies. As individual architects, we need to use each day to learn something new. We must maximize personal learning, transforming individual lessons learned into shared guidelines.</p>

<p>One of the problems I frequently see in organizations, particularly complex and international ones, is that they may need more natural spaces for group knowledge sharing. Consequently, the <a href="people">People Pillar</a> aims at creating spaces for sharing knowledge about architecture and technology. These spaces include but are not limited to regular update calls, knowledge-sharing sessions, or conferences.</p>

<p>In addition to creating spaces, as a community, we can further increase our learning value by deriving generalized insights from cross-group cases.</p>

<p>Lastly, one of the problems many organizations face is that due to their complexity and size, they have more challenges in introducing new technologies than their disruptors (Figure 3).</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/superglue/internalizing-tech-trends.png" alt="" />
<em><strong>Figure 3:</strong> One crucial aspect of Architects’ work is following external trends and finding pragmatic ways to introduce these trends in the organization. Credit: inspired by <a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/whats-hurry-building-digital-enterprise">thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/whats-hurry-building-digital-enterprise</a></em></p>

<p>We need more time to understand and utilize new technology developments while the number of new technologies is increasing due to, e.g., the continuous and accelerating evolution of cloud and mobile products. As architects, we must proactively identify relevant new technology developments. Based on our understanding of these developments, we must create pragmatic technology recommendations for concrete platforms across the organization.</p>

<p>The grounded architecture aims to accelerate the adoption of new technology and quick learning by providing more data to facilitate reflection and better connecting people to leverage each other’s explorations.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="adaptivity">Adaptivity</h2>

<p>The three elements of the grounded Architecture model, data, people, and strategy/governance platforms, provide a highly flexible and adaptive setting.</p>

<p>This adaptivity is driven by the independence of elements and the possibility of using the elements in different combinations. Here are some of the critical drivers of flexibility:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The data pillar, if implemented with a high level of automation, allows for quick extensions and reconfigurations to provide data for any change of direction. Extending the platform with new data should be easy after acquisitions or mergers. And the ability to group data at multiple levels supported the what-if scenario analysis (e.g., the impact of different reorganization scenarios). It defined a baseline to track changes in the organization.</li>
  <li>A strong data pillar provides crucial connections and feedback on the daily reality of each part of the organization.</li>
  <li>Grounding the architecture with data and people connections also makes the work of a Chief Architect much more flexible. As most architectural decisions can be delegated to well-aligned teams, a Chief Architect, typically the most experienced technologist, can spend more time on crucial strategic initiatives, such as defining cloud, data, or platform strategies or supporting decisions on mergers and acquisitions.</li>
  <li>Lastly, the structure of our architectural model enables a more sustainable architectural function. With an established <a href="data">Data Pillar</a> and a well-connected architect, the architecture can still benefit the organization even without a strong central team.</li>
</ul>

<p><br />
<img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/lego-g7d6cf2046_1920.png" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/painter06-3732158/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=3388163">Francis Ray</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=3388163">Pixabay</a>
</div>

<h2 id="questions-to-consider">Questions to Consider</h2>

<p>It is always essential to be thoughtful about the value and impact of your work. Ask yourself the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>How effective is your organization’s current architectural function at scale? How valuable are principles of Grounded Architecture to enhance its efficiency?</em></li>
  <li><em>To what extent does your organization use data to inform architectural decisions? What steps could you take to move your organization from opinion-based to more data-driven decision-making?</em></li>
  <li><em>How well-aligned are the different areas within your organization, and how does this affect your architectural function? Could the Data and People Pillars principles be utilized to improve alignment?</em></li>
  <li><em>What strategies does your organization currently have to foster organizational learning? How could the methods described in the Grounded Architecture model enhance this?</em></li>
  <li><em>How quickly can your organization adopt and utilize new technologies? How could your architecture practice accelerate this process?</em></li>
  <li><em>Consider the adaptivity of your organization’s architectural function. How could your architecture practice improve it?</em></li>
  <li><em>Reflecting on the value of the “data pillar” concept, how effectively is your organization tracking changes, supporting what-if scenario analysis, and defining baselines?</em></li>
  <li><em>What role does the Chief Architect play in your organization? Could their time be better utilized on strategic initiatives?</em></li>
  <li><em>How sustainable is the architectural function in your organization in the absence of a strong central team? Could implementing a Data Pillar and well-connected architects help mitigate this?</em></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When Grounded Architecture is in place, it can have a significant positive impact on the functioning of an organization: Executing At Scale, Increasing the Quality of Decision-Making with Data, Maximizing Organizational Alignment & Learning, Higher Adaptivity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Being Architect: Introduction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/being-architect" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being Architect: Introduction" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/being-architect</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/being-architect"><![CDATA[<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/arch/architect-3979490_1920.jpg" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/borevina-9505414/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=3979490">Borko Manigoda</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com//?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=3979490">Pixabay</a>
</div>
<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 140%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong>  Get an overview of topics related to what it means to be an architect, covered in this chapter.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>I introduce ideas and key lessons I learned about what it means to be an architect in practice.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p><br />
The following reflections provide some resources, ideas and key lessons I learned about what it means to be an architect in practice:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong><a href="superglue">Architects as Superglue</a></strong>: Architects in IT organizations should develop as “superglue,” people who hold architecture, technical details, business needs, and people together across a large organization or complex projects.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="impact">Skills</a></strong>: A typical skillset of an architects includes: hard (technical) skills, soft (people &amp; social) skills, and business skills.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="impact">Impact</a></strong>: Architects’ work is evaluated based the impact they’ve had on the organization. They must demonstrate that they identify, tackle, and deliver on strategic problems, have a deep and/or broad influence, and deliver solutions that few others can.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="behaviors">Leadership</a></strong>: My view of architecture leadership is inspired by David Marquet’s work and the Netflix’s valued behaviors.</li>
  <li><strong><a href="career">Architects’ Career Paths: Raising the Bar</a></strong>: Architects’ career paths ideally stem from a strong engineering background. Hiring architects requires constantly raising the bar to ensure a strong and diverse team structure.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I introduce ideas and key lessons I learned about what it means to be an architect in practice.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Architects as Superglue</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/superglue" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Architects as Superglue" /><published>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-21T22:12:01+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/superglue</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/superglue"><![CDATA[<style>
     h2 {
          margin-top: 40px;
     }
     h3 {
          margin-top: 40px;
     }
</style>

<p><img style="margin-top: -20px; width: 100%; height: 400px; object-fit: cover" src="assets/images/superglue/superglue.png" /></p>
<div style="font-size: 70%; margin-top: -16px; color: grey; margin-bottom: 12px">
</div>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>IN THIS SECTION, YOU WILL:</strong>  Understand the view on architects as superglue (people who hold architecture, technical details, business needs, and people together across a large organization or complex projects) and get valuable tips on developing “superglue” abilities.</p>

  <p><strong>KEY POINTS:</strong></p>

  <ul>
    <li>Architects in IT organizations should develop as “superglue,” people who hold architecture, technical details, business needs, and people together across a large organization or complex projects.</li>
    <li>Architects need to be technically strong. But their unique strengths should stem from being able to relate, or glue, technical issues with business and broader issues.</li>
    <li>Architects should stand on three legs: Skills, Impact, Leadership.</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>
<style>
 .quote {
     border-left: 8px solid skyblue;
     padding-left: 36px;
     margin-top: 30px;
     margin-bottom: 40px;
     font-size: 140%;
     font-style: normal;
     color:#888;
 }
    @media only screen and (max-width: 768px) {
        [class="quote"] {
            display: none;
        }
    }
</style>

<p><br />
In my view, architects in IT organizations should develop as “superglue.” I borrow the “superglue” view from <a href="https://saturn2016.sched.com/event/63m9/cant-find-superheroes-to-help-you-out-of-a-crisis-how-about-some-architecture-and-lots-of-superglue">Adam Bar-Niv and Amir Shenhav from Intel</a>. They pointed out that instead of the superhero, we need “superglue” architects - the people who hold architecture, technical details, business needs, and people together across large organizations or complex projects. More recently, Tanya Reilly presented a <a href="https://noidea.dog/glue">similar view</a> concerning software engineering positions.</p>

<p>The superglue characteristics mean serving as the organizational connective tissue, linking the “business wheelhouse” and the “engine room.” Architects, of course, need to be technically strong. But their unique strengths should stem from being able to relate, or glue, technical issues with business and broader issues.</p>

<div class="quote">
Architects, of course, need to be technically strong. But their unique strengths should stem from being able to relate, or glue, technical issues with business and broader issues.
</div>

<p>From discussions I’ve had with our technology leaders, engineers, and architects, the picture below has crystallized as a representation of the “superglue” metaphor for architects (Figure 1).</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/superglue/architect-as-superglue.png" alt="" />
<em><strong>Figure 1:</strong> Architects serve as a superglue, connecting development teams with business stakeholders while linking teams with the internal communities and the external world.</em></p>

<p>Architects must have good relationships with developer teams, local business stakeholders, and functions. Simultaneously, such a person needs to be well-connected with broader internal communities. External visibility is essential for architects, who can bring ideas from outside into the organization and promote the organization to the outside world.</p>

<p><br /></p>
<h2 id="superglue-abilities">Superglue Abilities</h2>

<p>Setting the architects’ goals to be “superglue” also requires some thought on developing architects as a superglue. Borrowing from Gregor Hohpe’s view on architect development from his book Software Architecture Elevator, I share the view that our architects should stand on three legs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Skills</li>
  <li>Impact</li>
  <li>leadership</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/images/superglue/architect-skills.png" alt="" />
<em><strong>Figure 2:</strong> Architect Profile: Skills + Impact + Leadership.</em></p>

<h3 id="skills">Skills</h3>

<p>Architects have to have proper skill sets. By skills, I mean possessing knowledge and the ability to apply relevant knowledge in practice. These skills should include both technical (e.g., cloud architecture or Kubernetes technology) as well as communication and influence skills.</p>

<p>A typical skillset of an architects includes:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Hard (technical) skills</strong>, including extensive knowledge of for both new technology and legacy technology stacks,</li>
  <li><strong>Soft skills</strong>, and</li>
  <li><strong>Business Domain knowledge</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p>The section <a href="skills">Skills</a> provides more details.</p>

<h3 id="impact">Impact</h3>

<p>Impact should be measured as a benefit for the business. Architects need to ensure that what they are doing profits the business:</p>
<ul>
  <li>They identify, tackle and deliver on <strong>strategic problems</strong> at the organization and area level.</li>
  <li>They have a <strong>track record of deep and/or broad impact</strong> on a product or technology area.</li>
  <li>They <strong>deliver solutions that few others can</strong>, either by your <strong>heavy lifting</strong> or the <strong>ability to orchestrate large group efforts</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Architects need to get out into the world and make an impact. Architects that do not make an impact <strong>do not have a place in a for-profit business</strong>.</p>

<p>Examples of such impact may include:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Aligning</strong> business, product, technology and organizatinal strategies (see <a href="storm">this section</a> for more details),</li>
  <li><strong>Process</strong> optimizations and improvements, with real measurable impact on work of an organization,</li>
  <li><strong>Cost</strong> optimizations of systems, based on data informed decisions,</li>
  <li>Developing pragmatic <strong>technology strategies</strong>, helping business reach goals in a sustainable way,</li>
  <li>Driving <strong>delivery of products</strong>, supporting teams to increase quality and speed of delivery,</li>
  <li>Supporting <strong>business innovation</strong>, bringing new ideas in a pragmatic way aligned with business strategy and goals.</li>
</ul>

<p>The section <a href="impact">Impact</a> provides more details.
In my view, architects in IT organizations should develop as “superglue.”</p>

<h3 id="leadership">Leadership</h3>

<p>Lleadership acknowledges that experienced architects should do more than make architecture:</p>
<ul>
  <li>They are a <strong>role model for others</strong> in the company on both the <strong>technical</strong> and <strong>cultural</strong> front.</li>
  <li>Their <strong>technical influence</strong> may extend <strong>beyond you organization and reach the industry at large</strong>.</li>
  <li>They <strong>lead efforts</strong> that <strong>solve important problems</strong> at the engineering area level.</li>
  <li>They may <strong>contribute to the broader technical community</strong> through <strong>tech talks</strong>, <strong>education</strong>, <strong>publications</strong>, <strong>open source projects</strong>, etc.</li>
  <li>They <strong>raise the bar of the engineering culture</strong> across the company.</li>
</ul>

<p>Mentoring junior architects is the most crucial aspect of senior architects’ leadership. Feedback cycles in (software) architecture are inherently slow. Mentoring can save new architects many years of learning by doing and making mistakes. The <a href="people">People Pillar</a> should create spaces for such coaching and collaborations.</p>

<p>The section <a href="leadership">Leadership</a> provides more details.</p>

<h2 id="balanced-development">Balanced Development</h2>

<p>Architects need to have a minimal “length” of all of these “legs” to be successful (Figure 3). For instance, having skills and impact without leadership frequently leads to hitting a glass ceiling. Such architects plateau at an intermediate level and cannot lead the company to innovative or transformative solutions. Leadership without impact lacks foundation and may signal that you have become an ivory tower architect with a weak relation to reality. And having impact and leadership qualities but no skills leads to impractical decisions not informed by in-depth knowledge.</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/arch/architect-legs.png" alt="" />
<em><strong>Figure 3:</strong> Architects need to have a minimal “length” of all of these “legs” to be successful.</em></p>

<h2 id="questions-to-consider">Questions to Consider</h2>

<p>Being a superglue architect means constantly developing and redefining your role to benefit a changing organization. Ask yourself the following questions:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>How well do you think you currently embody the characteristics of a “superglue” architect? Which areas could you improve on to become more effective in this role?</em></li>
  <li><em>Reflect on your ability to connect the “business wheelhouse” and the “engine room” within your organization. How effectively do you bridge the gap between technical issues and business needs?</em></li>
  <li><em>How strong are your relationships with developer teams, local business stakeholders, and broader internal communities? What strategies could you employ to strengthen these connections?</em></li>
  <li><em>How much external visibility do you currently have? How could this be enhanced to promote the flow of ideas into and out of the organization?</em></li>
  <li><em>Considering the three legs of a successful architect (skills, impact, leadership), which do you consider your strongest? Which might need more development?</em></li>
  <li><em>Assess your technical skills and ability to apply this knowledge in practice. How well do you balance hard (technical) skills, soft skills, and business domain knowledge?</em></li>
  <li><em>How do you currently measure your impact within your organization? Could you identify and address more strategic problems to benefit the business?</em></li>
  <li><em>Reflect on your leadership abilities. How are you acting as a role model within your organization and contributing to the broader technical community?</em></li>
  <li><em>How do you balance skill development, impact, and leadership? Where should you focus more on ensuring a balanced development as an architect?</em></li>
  <li><em>In what ways could you be more of a mentor for junior architects? What spaces could you create or utilize to facilitate more effective coaching and collaboration?</em></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>by Željko Obrenović (obren.io)</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Architects in IT organizations should develop as “superglue,” people who hold architecture, technical details, business needs, and people together across a large organization or complex projects.]]></summary></entry></feed>